SARANSH GUPTA

+91 9530277421 ◊ Rajasthan, India

Email \(\rightarrow Linkedin \(\rightarrow GitHub \(\rightarrow Google Scholar \(\rightarrow Website \)

OBJECTIVE

Data Scientist with 2+ years of experience developing machine learning models and transforming data science prototypes into production grade solutions. Optimizes and improves NLP systems on a consistent basis by evaluating strategies and testing changes in machine learning models.

EDUCATION

Indian Institute of Technology Kharagpur

Integrated Master of Technology in Engineering Product Design

2017 - 2022

Grade: 8.09 / 10

SKILLS

Technical Skills

Soft Skills

Cr

Python, PyTorch, Transformers, BERT, Transfer Learning, scikit-learn, TensorFlow Critical thinking, Problem-Solving, Team Player, Quick learner, Communication

PUBLICATIONS

- S. Gupta et al. "Integrative Network Modeling Highlights the Crucial Roles of Rho-GDI Signaling Pathway in the Progression of Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer" in IEEE JBHI, 2022, doi: 10.1109/JBHI.2022.3190038
- Entity-aware Question-Answer Extraction for Shopping Guidance, Amazon Machine Learning Conference

WORK EXPERIENCE

American Express

Aug 2022 - Present

Engineer-III

Gurugram, Haryana, India

Project 1: Failure cause identification of applications on generated Incident for their automated resolve

- Implemented a Question-Answer based strategy on top of raw dataset to identify failure cause of applications
- Achieved **F1 Score of 0.84** by fine tuning a pre-trained **BERT** based Question-Answering model

Project 2: Automation of various repetitive tasks to save the manual efforts

- Improved the data security by developing an automatic **PII data** identification and encryption tool
- Reduced 12 business hours per month by automating the application availability report generation process
- Automated resolutions for certain repetitive Incidents saving on an average 2 business hours every day

Tools and Software: Python, PyTorch, Pandas, NumPy, matplotlib

Amazon Development Centre India

Applied Scientist - Intern

Jan 2022 - June 2022 Bengaluru, Karnataka, India

Project: Generate Pre-curated Question Bank (PCQB) by Question and Answer extraction from articles

- Developed a Transformers-based two-step model for **Question Generation** followed by the **answer extraction**
- Scrapped Texts, People Also Ask (PAA) questions and answers using queries related to the E- Commerce domain
- Achieved a Perplexity score of 82.3 on Question Generation by fine-tuning a T5 model on the PAA dataset
- Attained F-1 score of 0.79 on the answer extraction task by fine-tuning the T5-large model on the PAA dataset
- Deployed the two-step model pipeline on the streamlit-based **demo web application** that accepts user input

Tools and Software: Python, PyTorch, Transfer Learning, PAA, T5 Model, BERT, streamlit

ZS Associates Jan 2021 – June 2021

Data Science Associate - Intern

Bengaluru, Karnataka, India

Project 1: Extract biomedical text dataset, identify entities, and classify if there exists a relation between entities

- Created a pipeline to extract texts from PubMed database, identifying entities using Selenium and PubTator
- Implemented Binary Classification rules, devised four labeling functions using bio-verbs, co- occurrence of entities
- Generated a training dataset utilizing the four labeling functions in Snorkel by applying the Weak Supervision
- Achieved **F1 score of 0.88** on the test dataset in relation-classification by fine-tuning RoBERTa base model

Project 2: Identify the type of relationship between two entities if it exists from the result of the Project-1

- Created a new set of three labeling functions for relation-type identification by using the results of the project-1
- Attained F1 score of 0.83 on the test dataset using XGBoost Model followed by feature engineering

Tools and Software: Python, PyTorch, Transfer Learning, Medline-Plus API, PubTator, Selenium, Snorkel

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Emory University

Jul 2022 - Present

Volunteer Researcher (remote)

Atlanta, GA, USA

Project: Predict the type of Venous thromboembolism (VTE), from the medical diagnosis and clinical Impressions

- Reduced manual adjudication of dataset by 20 times using pegasus paraphrasing model on sample dataset
- Achieved **F1 score of 0.97** in predicting the type of VTE on test dataset by fine-tuning a **Bio- BERT** model
- Improved F1 score on test dataset by **20 percent** by deploying **paraphrasing** and Bio-BERT finetuning pipeline **Tools and Software:** Python, PyTorch, Transfer Learning, pegasus model, BERT

Osaka University

Jan 2020 - Dec 2020

Research Assistant (remote)

Ibaraki, Osaka, Japan

Project: Predict Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer (NSCLC) using Machine Learning, identify potential drug targets

- Extracted 412 essential genes out of 10,077 by applying Boruta Feature selection on gene expression dataset
- Obtained F-1 score of 1.0 on validation, 0.98 on test dataset by using the XGBoost model to predict NSCLC
- Predicted drug targets for the NSCLC by simulating a Bayesian Network Model on Rho-GDI signaling pathway
- Discovered methodology leads to an accurate treatment of the disease impacting **85%** of the lung cancer patients **Tools and Software:** Python, Pandas, NumPy, matplotlib, XGBoost, Bayesian Network, networkX

INTERNSHIPS

Sapio Analytics April 2020 - June 2020

Data Analyst - Intern

Mumbai, Maharashtra, India

Project: Build a data-driven Decision Support System for the prediction of COVID-19 at the hyper-local level

- Fabricated SEIRD model using Migration, Lockdown conditions, reduced RMSE up to 4.8% by tuning parameters
- The Govt. Of Telangana has used the application to mitigate COVID-19 while maximizing the economic activities

Tools and Software: Python, MySQL, scikit-learn, SciPy, AWS Server, NumPy, pandas, Plotly, joblib

ACHIEVEMENTS

- Conferred Blue-Award at the American Express for impactful contribution to the organization in Jan 2023
- Received scholarship of 248 USD for Harvard College Project for Asian International Relations conference 2022
- Featured as one of the Top 30 Undergraduate Achievers of IIT Kharagpur in the UG Achievers Directory 2020
- Awarded scholarship of **2200€** by The A*Midex Foundation of Aix-Marseille University, **France**, Feb 2020
- Selected among Top 5 percent out of all for the summer fellowship at Institute of Science Technology Austria
- Featured in the ISE Newsletter Autumn-2020 under Department Spotlight of ISE fights COVID- 19, 2020

COMPETITIONS AND CONFERENCES

•	Annual Amazon Machine Learning Conference (AMLC) – Bengaluru, Karnataka	Aug 2022
•	23rd World Business Dialogue, Creation Lab at Evonik - Cologne, Germany	Jun 2022
•	Amazon ML Summer School 2021: Offered PPI	Jul 2021
•	International Conference on Human Interaction Emerging Technologies	Aug 2020
•	Young Data Scientists annual meetup at Kaggle - days, Dubai World Trade Centre	Mar 2020
•	Winner at Databuzz 2020 conducted by DoMS, IIT Madras	Jan 2020

LEADERSHIP

- Mentored 5 students, actively involved in facilitating their one-one sessions and doubt clearing sessions
- Part of the GOLD-WINNING water polo team of Azad Hall of Residence at Inter-hall general championship, 2019
- Raised sponsorship of INR 51,000/- at KHOJ, the treasure hunt event organized by Azad Hall of Residence, 2019
- Managed a technical workshop on SolidWorks at Jadavpur University organized by teamKART, IIT Kharagpur

DECLARATION

I solemnly declare that the above information is correct to the best of my knowledge and belief.